A Guide to the Appalachian Oral History Project 1986-91
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Appalachian Oral History Project 1986-91
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms1993-025
4 containers; 1.25 cu. ft.
Collection contains oral history interview cassette tapes and tape logs for 23 interviews conducted by students with 25 interviewees in the local community. Most interviews were collected as part of a 1991 Appalachian Community Studies class of Professor Jean Speer of the Department of Humanities at Virginia Tech. Unless noted, interviews have not been transcribed. For some interviewees, there is a student paper based on the interview.
The Appalachian Oral History Project was donated to the Special Collections in 1993.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research with the exception of tapes and transcripts for which there are no oral history release forms. Box four of the collection is restricted with no access because release forms are unavailable for these interviews.
Biographical/Historical Information
Most of the interviews in the collection were conducted as part of an Appalachian Oral History project in an 1991 Appalachian Community Studies class taught by Professor Jean Speer. With the possible exception of Kenneth Webb, interviewees resided in the New River Valley.
Scope and Content Information
The collection covers 1986-91, with the bulk of the collection in the year 1991. Collection consists of interview tapes and interview tape logs of oral history interviews conducted by student interviewers in Dr. Jean Speer's Appalachian Community Studies class in the Department of Humanities at Virginia Tech, and by a student of Dr. Bohland. Interviewees include Frank W. Bannister, Lillie A. Beavers, Julia T. Bratton, Thomas Cartmel Brown, Carol M. Caldwell, Freeman A. Cockram, Virginia B. Creger, Robert and Josephine Dolinger, Ora Evans, Donald R. Fessler, Anne W. Frame, David H. Halsey, Mildred S. Richardson, Judith C. Sale, and Elizabeth M. Weatherford. Restricted interviews include Georgia Croy, Carlton Harmon, Jack and Lillian Minnick, and Ellison A. Smyth. Transcript available for Kenneth S. Hamblin, Sr., interview. The collection also includes undated tapes of the Shapenote Singing School and a tape of Presentation Music/Interview with Keith Webb, Arkansas Shapenote Gathering Concert.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by interviewee. Box 1 contains documentation and notes, boxes 2 and 3 contain tapes, and box 4 contains restricted tapes and tape logs.
Contents List
- Appalachian Oral History Project 1986-91
  - "The Authorized Life History of Frank W. Bannister as told to Erin J. O'Leary" March, 1991 (Box-folder 1-1)
    Frank W. Bannister interview by Erin O'Leary, tape log
  - Lillie A. Beavers interview by K. Michael Hanna October 13, 1986, October 31, 1986, October 7, 1987 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Lillie A. Beavers interview by Shawn Hash, tape log 1991 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Julia T. Bratton interview by Margaret G. Sale, tape log March 14, 1991 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - "Oral History Report of Thomas Cartmel Brown" January 29, 1991 (Box-folder 1-5)
    Thomas Cartmel Brown interview by Margaret Ann Facenda, tape log and photographs
  - Carol M. Caldwell interview by Julie Ann Brunges, March 1, 1991 (Box-folder 1-6)
    tape log, notes, and photographs of Catawba and Dragon's Tooth
  - Freeman A. Cockram interview by Holly Lord, tape log, March 23, 1991 (Box-folder 1-7)
    Mr. Cockram is the owner of Cockram's Store in Floyd.
  - Virginia B. Creger interview by Margaret G. Sale, tape log February 28, 1991 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Robert and Josephine Dolinger interview by Lesley Leonard, tape catalog and photographs May 17, 1987 (Box-folder 1-9)
    Mr. Dolinger was caretaker at Mountain Lake.
  - "Living with Memories - Ora Evans: A Life History" January 30, 1991 (Box-folder 1-10)
    Ora Evans interview by Heather Dorsey, tape log
  - "An Oral History: Part of the Appalachian Story" February 4, 1991 (Box-folder 1-11)
    Donald R. Fessler interview by Christina Small, tape log
  - Ann W. Frame interview by Margaret G. Sale, tape log February 19, 1991 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - David H. Halsey interview by Helena D. May, tape log March 15, 1991 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Kenneth S. Hamblin, Sr., interview by Kimberly W. Pruett, March 5, 1991 (Box-folder 1-14)
    tape transcript and ephemera mounted on paper. Mr. Hamblin is a dulcimer maker.
  - Perry C. and Vergie Holt interview by Trudy Teter, February 7, 1991 (Box-folder 1-15)
    tape log and interview questions; "Appalachian Oral History Project"
  - Mildred S. Richardson interview by Margaret G. Sale, tape log March 3, 1991 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Judith Crowell interview by Margaret Sale, tape log March 13, 1991 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Elizabeth M. Wetherford interview by Beverly Duncan, tape log March 12, 1991 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Interview cassette tapes 1986-91, n.d. (Box 2)
    Frank Bannister (2); Lillie A. Beavers (3 by Hanna; 2 by Hash); Julia Bratton (1); Thomas Cartmel Brown (3); Carol Caldwell (1); Freeman Cockram (1); Virginia Creger (1); Georgia Croy (3); Robert and Josephine Dolinger (2).
  - Interview cassette tapes 1986-91, n.d. (Box 3)
    Ora Evans (3); Don Fessler (2); Anne Frame and Dr. Luke Frame (1); David Halsey (1); Perry and Vergie Holt (3); Mildred Richardson (1); Judith Sale (1); Elizabeth Wetherford Nurse (3); Shapenote Singing School (Wednesday night, 1; Thursday night, 2); Presentation Music/Interview with Keith Webb (side A); Arkansas Shapenote Gathering Concert (side B)
    Microcassette Tapes: Kenneth Hamblin (3)
  - Georgia Croy interview by Gustavo Colon, tape logs and 3 cassettes. Restricted. February 1, 1991, February 8, 1991, February 22, 1991, March 30, 1991 (Box-folder 4-19)
  - Carlton Harmon interview by Holly Lord, tape cassette. No documentation. Restricted. n.d. (Box-folder 4-20)
  - Jack and Lillian Minnick interview by Stacey R. Minnick, cassette n.d. (Box-folder 4-21)
  - Ellison A. Smyth interview by unknown interviewer, tape log February 5, 1991 (Box-folder 4-22)
  - Keith Webb interview by Stephanie Meredith, tape log n.d. (Box-folder 4-23)